<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %W  copyrigh.xml              GAP documentation                      LDFM -->
<!-- %W                                                                 & SMCS -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %H  @(#)<M>Id: copyrigh.msk,v 1.6 2004/02/13 17:38:52 gap Exp </M> -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %Y  Copyright 1997,  Lehrstuhl D für Mathematik,   RWTH Aachen, Germany -->
<!-- %Y  Copyright (C) 2002, The GAP Group -->
<!-- %% -->


Copyright &copyright; (1987-&RELEASEYEAR;) by the &GAP; Group, 
<P/>
incorporating the Copyright &copyright; 1999, 2000  by
        School of Mathematical and Computational Sciences,
        University of St&nbsp;Andrews,
        North Haugh, St&nbsp;Andrews, Fife KY16 9SS, Scotland
<P/>
being the Copyright &copyright; 1992 by
        Lehrstuhl D für Mathematik, RWTH,
        52056 Aachen, Germany,
transferred to St&nbsp;Andrews on July 21st, 1997.
<P/>
except for files in the distribution, which have an explicit different
copyright statement. In particular, the copyright of packages distributed
with &GAP; is usually with the package authors or their institutions.
<P/>
&GAP; is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
(at your option) any later version. For details, see 
the file <F>GPL</F> in the <F>etc</F> directory of the &GAP; distribution or see
<URL>http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html</URL>.
<P/>
If you obtain &GAP; please send us a short notice to that effect, e.g.,
an e-mail message to the address <Email>support@gap-system.org</Email>. 
This helps us to keep track of the number of &GAP; users.
<P/>
If you publish a mathematical result that was partly obtained using
&GAP;, please cite &GAP;, just as you would cite another paper that you
used (see below for sample citation). Also we would appreciate if you
could inform us about such a paper, which we will add to the &GAP;
<URL Text="bibliography">https://www.gap-system.org/Doc/Bib/bib.html</URL>.
<P/>
Specifically, please refer to
<P/>
<Listing>
[GAP] The GAP Group, GAP - Groups, Algorithms, and Programming,
      Version &VERSIONNUMBER;; &RELEASEYEAR; (https://www.gap-system.org)
</Listing>
<P/>
You are permitted to modify and redistribute &GAP;, but you are not
allowed to restrict further redistribution. That is to say proprietary
modifications will not be allowed. We want all versions of &GAP; to
remain free.
<P/>
If you  modify any part of &GAP; and redistribute it,  you must supply a
<F>README</F> document. This should specify what modifications you made in
which files. We do not want to take credit or be blamed for your
modifications.
<P/>
Of course we are interested in all of your modifications. In particular
we would like to see bug-fixes, improvements and new functions. So again
we would appreciate it if you would inform us about all modifications you
make.
<P/>
In addition to the general copyright for &GAP; set forth above,
the following terms apply to the versions of &GAP; for Windows.
<P/>
The executable of &GAP; for Windows that we distribute was compiled with
the <C>gcc</C> compiler supplied with <Package>Cygwin</Package> installation
(<URL>http://cygwin.com/</URL>).
<P/>
The GNU C compiler is
<P/>
<E>Copyright &copyright; 2010 Free Software Foundation, Inc.</E>
<P/>
under the terms of the GNU General Public License (GPL).
<P/>
The <Package>Cygwin</Package> API library is also covered by the GNU GPL. 
The executable we provide is linked against this library (and in the process 
includes GPL'd <Package>Cygwin</Package> glue code). This means that the 
executable falls under the GPL too, which it does anyhow.
<P/>
The <F>cyggcc_s-1.dll</F>, <F>cygncurses-10.dll</F>, <F>cygncursesw-10.dll</F>,
<F>cygpanel-10.dll</F>, <F>cygpopt-0.dll</F>, <F>cygreadline7.dll</F>,
<F>cygstart.exe</F>, <F>cygwin1.dll</F>, <F>libW11.dll</F>, <F>mintty.exe</F>, 
<F>rxvt.exe</F> and <F>regtool.exe</F> are taken unmodified from the 
<Package>Cygwin</Package> distribution. They are copyright by RedHat Software
and released under the GPL. For more information on <Package>Cygwin</Package>,
see <URL>http://www.cygwin.com</URL>. 
<P/>
Please contact <Email>support@gap-system.org</Email> if you need further information.




<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %E -->

