<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %W  moreinfo.xml              GAP documentation         Joachim Neubueser -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %H  @(#)<M>Id: preface.tex,v 4.44 2006/06/27 21:37:08 gap Exp </M> -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %Y  Copyright (C) 1997, Lehrstuhl D für Mathematik, RWTH Aachen, Germany -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %%  This file contains a part of the preface to the tutorial and reference manual -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->

Information about &GAP; is best obtained from the &GAP; website
<P/>
	<URL>https://www.gap-system.org</URL>
<P/>
There you will find, amongst other things
<List>
<Item>
directions to the sites from which you can download the
current &GAP; distribution, all accepted and deposited &GAP; packages,
and a selection of other contributions.
</Item>
<Item>
the &GAP; manual and an archive of the <C>gap-forum</C> mailing
list, formatted for reading with a Web browser, and indexed for
searching.
</Item>
<Item>
information about &GAP; developers, and about the email
addresses available for comment, discussion and support.
</Item>
</List>
<P/>
<P/>
We would particularly ask you to note the following things:
<List>
<Item>
The &GAP; Forum &ndash; an email discussion forum for comments,
discussions or questions about &GAP;. You must subscribe to the list
before you can post to it, see the website for details.
In particular we will announce new releases in this mailing list.
</Item>
<Item>
The email address <Email>support@gap-system.org</Email> to which you
are asked to send any questions or bug reports which do not seem likely
to be of interest to the whole &GAP; Forum. Please give a 
(short, if possible) self-contained excerpt of a &GAP;
session containing both input and output that illustrates your problem 
(including comments of why you think it is a bug) and state the type of
the machine, operating system, (compiler used, if UNIX/Linux) and the 
version of &GAP; you are using (the first line after the &GAP;&nbsp;4 
banner starting <C>GAP, Version 4...</C>).
</Item>
<Item>
We also ask you to send a brief message to 
<Email>support@gap-system.org</Email> when you install &GAP;.
</Item>
<Item>
The correct form of citation of &GAP;, which we ask you use
whenever you publish scientific results obtained using &GAP;.
</Item>
</List>
<P/>
It finally remains for us to wish you all pleasure and success in using
&GAP;, and to invite your constructive comment and criticism.
<P/>
<P/>
<P/>
The GAP Group,
<P/>
&RELEASEDAY;

<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %E -->

