<!-- 

  afterrecog.xml          recog package documentation          Max Neunhoeffer
                                                                   Ákos Seress

         Copyright (C) 2005, Lehrstuhl D für Mathematik, RWTH-Aachen

This chapter shows what one can do after a successfull recognition.

-->

<Chapter Label="afterrecog">
<Heading>After successfull recognition</Heading>

This chapter explains, what one can do with recognition info records
after a successfull recognition (and possibly verification).<P/>

Of course, one can inspect the whole tree of recognition info records
just by looking at the stored attribute values. Moreover, constructive
membership tests can be performed using the function 
<Ref Func="SLPforElement"/>, thereby writing an arbitrary element
in terms of the nice generators, which are stored in the attribute
<Ref Attr="nicegens"/>. If <C>fail</C> is returned, then the
element in question does not lie in the recognised group or
the recognition made an error.<P/>

<Section>
    <Heading>Functions and methods for recognition info records</Heading>

If you need an element explicitly written in terms of the original
generators, you can use the following function:

<ManSection>
<Func Name="SLPforNiceGens" Arg="ri"/>
<Returns>an SLP expressing the nice generators in the original ones</Returns>
<Description>
    This function assembles a possibly quite large straight line program
    expressing the nice generators in terms of the original ones by using
    the locally stored information in the recognition tree recursively.<P/>
    You can concatenate straight line programs in the nice generators with
    the result of this function to explicitly write an element in terms
    of the original generators.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Meth Name="Size" Arg="ri"/>
<Returns>the size of the recognised group</Returns>
<Description>
    This method calculates the size of the recognised group
    by multiplying the size of the factor and the kernel recursively.
    It is assumed that leaf nodes know already or can calculate the
    size of their group.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Func Name="DisplayCompositionFactors" Arg="ri"/>
<Returns>nothing</Returns>
<Description>
    This function displays a composition series by using the recursive
    recognition tree. It only works, if the usual operation
    <Ref Oper="CompositionSeries" BookName="ref"/> works for all
    leaves.
</Description>
</ManSection>

</Section>

<!-- ############################################################ -->

</Chapter>
