<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!-- $Id: manual.xml,v 1.7 2009/05/31 21:50:11 alexk Exp $ -->

<!DOCTYPE Book SYSTEM "gapdoc.dtd"
[<!ENTITY LAGUNA "<Package>LAGUNA</Package>">]
[<!ENTITY UnitLib "<Package>UnitLib</Package>">]
[<!ENTITY QaoS "<Package>Qaos</Package>">]
[<!ENTITY SCSCP "<Package>SCSCP</Package>">]
[<!ENTITY ParGAP "<Package>ParGAP</Package>">] >

<Book Name="UnitLib">

<TitlePage>
  <Title>&UnitLib;</Title>
  <Subtitle>The library of normalized unit groups of modular group algebras</Subtitle>
  <Version>Version 3.0.0</Version>

  <Author>Alexander Konovalov
          <Email>konovalov@member.ams.org</Email>
	      <Homepage>http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/&tilde;alexk/</Homepage>
          <Address>
            School of Computer Science<Br/>
            University of St Andrews<Br/>
            Jack Cole Building, North Haugh,<Br/>
            St Andrews, Fife, KY16 9SX, Scotland
          </Address> 
  </Author>

  <Author>Elena Yakimenko
          <Email>k-algebra@zsu.zp.ua</Email>
          <Address>
            Department of Mathematics<Br/>
            Zaporozhye National University<Br/>
            Ul.Zhukovskogo, 66, Zaporozhye<Br/>
	        69600 Ukraine
          </Address> 
  </Author>

  <Date>31 May 2009</Date>

<Abstract>

<Index Key="UnitLib package">&UnitLib; package</Index> 

The &UnitLib; package extends the &LAGUNA; package and provides the 
library of normalized unit groups of modular group algebras of all 
finite <M>p</M>-groups of order not greater than 243 over the field 
of <M>p</M> elements.
<P/>
It also contains a parallel implementation of the computation of the 
normalized unit group of a modular group algebra of a finite 
<M>p</M>-group (which should be retrieved from the &GAP; Small Groups 
Library) over the field of <M>p</M> elements.
</Abstract>

<Copyright>
  &copyright; 2006-2009 by Alexander Konovalov and Elena Yakimenko<P/>

  &UnitLib; is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it 
  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by 
  the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or 
  (at your option) any later version. For details, see the FSF's own site
  <URL>http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html</URL>.<P/>

  If you obtained &UnitLib;, we would be grateful for a short notification
  sent to one of the authors.<P/>

  If you publish a result which was partially obtained with the usage of
  &UnitLib;, please cite it in the following form:<P/>

  A. Konovalov and E. Yakimenko. 
  <E>UnitLib --- The library of normalized unit groups of modular group 
     algebras, Version 3.0.0;</E> 2009 
     (<URL>http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/&tilde;alexk/unitlib.htm</URL>).
</Copyright>
  
<Acknowledgements>
The first version of the package (as well as the subsequent version 2.1)
was released in 2006, when the first author was a postdoctoral 
research collaborator at the Vrije Universiteit Brussels, Belgium. 
It is a pleasure of the first author to express his gratitude to 
Prof. Dr. Eric Jespers for his warm hospitality and to acknowledge 
the support provided by the Francqui Stichting grant ADSI107.
<P/>

Both authors are very grateful to the members of the &GAP; team: 
Thomas Breuer, Stefan Kohl and Frank L&#252;beck for helpful suggestions. 
We would like to acknowledge Bettina Eick for communicating the package,
and the referee for testing &UnitLib; and useful comments. 
Finally, we wish to thank the Centre for Interdisciplinary Research in 
Computational Algebra of the University of St Andrews and the 
Computational Cluster of the Kiev National Taras Shevchenko University
for offering their computer facilities for computations.
</Acknowledgements>

</TitlePage>

<TableOfContents/>

<Body>

<#Include SYSTEM "intro.xml">
<#Include SYSTEM "funct.xml"> 
<#Include SYSTEM "tech.xml">
<#Include SYSTEM "example.xml">

</Body>

<Bibliography Databases="manual"/>

<TheIndex/>

</Book>