
<!--  @(#)$Id: introduc.xml,v 1.2 2008/11/14 17:02:55 gap Exp $ -->

<Chapter Label="ch:introduction">
<Heading>Introduction to the &GAP; Character Table Library</Heading>

The usefulness of &GAP; for character theoretic tasks depends on the
availability of many known character tables,
and there is a lot of character tables in the &GAP; table library.
Of course, this library is <Q>open</Q> in the sense that it shall be extended.
So we would be grateful for any further tables of interest
sent to us for inclusion into our library.
Please offer interesting new character tables via e-mail
to <Email>sam@math.rwth-aachen.de</Email>.
<!-- A cross-reference to this address is at the end of another chapter! -->

<P/>

It depends on your &GAP; installation whether the character table library
is available.
You can check this as follows.

<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> InstalledPackageVersion( "ctbllib" ) <> fail;
true
]]></Example>

<P/>

If the result is <K>false</K> then the library is not installed,
and you may ask your system administrator for installing it,
or install the library in your home directory,
see&nbsp;<Ref Sect="sec:install"/>.

<P/>

For general information about character tables in &GAP;,
see Chapter&nbsp;<Ref Chap="Character Tables" BookName="ref"/>.

<P/>

The <F>doc</F> directory of the &GAP; Character Table Library contains
several files with demonstrations of computations with character tables.
Currently these are <F>ambigfus.pdf</F>, <F>ctbldeco.pdf</F>,
<F>ctblj4.pdf</F>, <F>ctblpope.pdf</F>, <F>ctocenex.pdf</F>,
<F>multfree.pdf</F>, and <F>multfre2.pdf</F>.

<P/>

If you use the &GAP; Character Table Library to solve a problem then
please send a short email to <Email>sam@math.rwth-aachen.de</Email> about it.
The &GAP; Character Table Library database should be referenced
with the entry&nbsp;<Cite Key="CTblLib1.1.3"/>
in the bibliography of this manual.

<P/>

For referencing the &GAP; system in general,
use the entry&nbsp;<Cite Key="GAP4"/> in the bibliography of this manual.


<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<Section Label="sec:history">
<Heading>History of the &GAP; Character Table Library</Heading>

The first version of the &GAP; Character Table Library was released with
&GAP;&nbsp;3.1 in March 1992.

<P/>

It was the first aim of this library to continue the character table library
of the &CAS; system (see <Cite Key="NPP84"/>) in &GAP;,
as a part of the process of reimplementing the algorithms of &CAS; in &GAP;,
see&nbsp;<Ref Sect="History of Character Theory Stuff in GAP"
BookName="ref"/>.
&GAP;&nbsp;3.1 provided only very restricted methods for computing character
tables from groups,
so its character theory part was concerned mainly with library tables.

<P/>

A second aspect of the character table library was to make all character
tables shown in the &ATLAS; of Finite Groups
<Cite Key="CCN85"/> available in &GAP;.
In fact &GAP; turned out to provide a very good environment for
systematic checks of these character tables.

<P/>

To some extent,
the access to the (ordinary) character tables in&nbsp;<Cite Key="CCN85"/>
was a prerequisite for storing also the corresponding Brauer character tables
in the &GAP; Character Table Library.
Already &GAP;&nbsp;3.1 contained many of these tables.
They have been computed mainly <Q>outside of &GAP;</Q>,
using the methods described in&nbsp;<Cite Key="HJLP92"/>,
and part of the library has been published in the &ATLAS;
of Brauer Characters <Cite Key="JLPW95"/>.
One of the roles of &GAP; was again to perform systematic checks.

<P/>
Besides these projects, many individual character tables have been added
to the &GAP; Character Table Library since the times of &GAP;&nbsp;3.1.
They were computed from groups or with character theoretic methods
or using a combination of these two possibilities
(see, e.&nbsp;g., <Cite Key="NPP84"/> and <Cite Key="LP91"/>).

<P/>

Section&nbsp;<Ref Sect="sec:contents"/> lists some of the sources.
The changes in the &GAP; Character Table Library since the release of
&GAP;&nbsp;4.1 (in July 1999) are individually documented in the file
<F>ctbldiff.pdf</F>
which can be found in the <F>doc</F> directory of the package.

<P/>

In the meantime, a rudimentary interface between groups in &GAP; and the
tables in the &GAP; Character Table Library has been provided,
see&nbsp;<Ref Sect="The Interface between Character Tables and Groups"
BookName="ref"/>.
Similarly, there is an interface to the &GAP; Libary of Tables of Marks,
see&nbsp;<Ref
Sect="The Interface between Tables of Marks and Character Tables"
BookName="ref"/>.

<P/>

Currently the main focus in the development of the &GAP; Character Table
Library is --besides the addition of tables that appear to be interesting--
the better interaction with other databases,
such as the &ATLAS; of Group Representations
(see the &GAP;&nbsp;4 package <Package>AtlasRep</Package>),
and an improvement of the <Q>database</Q> aspect
of the character table library itself,
for example by providing a <Q>WWW table of contents</Q>.

<P/>

Until the release of &GAP;&nbsp;4.3 in spring 2002,
the &GAP; Character Table Library had been a part of the main &GAP;
library.
With &GAP;&nbsp;4.3, it was <Q>split off</Q> as a &GAP; package.

</Section>


<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<Section Label="sec:install">
<Heading>Installing the &GAP; Character Table Library</Heading>

To install the package unpack the archive file in a
directory in the <F>pkg</F> directory of your local copy of &GAP;&nbsp;4.
This might be the <F>pkg</F> directory of the &GAP;&nbsp;4 home directory,
see Section&nbsp;<Ref Sect="Installing a GAP Package" BookName="ref"/>
for details.
It is however also possible to keep an additional <F>pkg</F> directory
in your private directories,
see&nbsp;<Ref Sect="GAP Root Directory" BookName="ref"/>.
The latter possibility <E>must</E> be chosen if you do not have write access
to the &GAP; root directory.

<P/>

The package consists entirely of &GAP; code,
no external binaries need to be compiled.

<P/>

<#Include Label="testinst">

<!-- %T add a section "Sanity Checks for ..."! -->

PDF and HTML versions of the package manual are available
in the <F>doc</F> directory of the package.

</Section>


<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<Section Label="sec:loading">
<Heading>Loading the &GAP; Character Table Library</Heading>

The &GAP; Character Table Library may be loaded automatically when &GAP;
is started,
or it has to be loaded within &GAP; as follows.

<P/>

<Example>
gap> LoadPackage( "ctbllib" );
true
</Example>

<P/>

See&nbsp;<Ref Sect="Loading a GAP Package" BookName="ref"/>
for details about these alternatives;
also the possibility to disable automatic loading of the package
is described in this manual section.
The default is that the &GAP; Character Table Library is loaded
automatically.

<P/>

If the main memory of your computer is large enough then it may save time
to keep all data in memory once they have been loaded,
see&nbsp;<Ref Func="CTblLibSetUnload"/>.

</Section>


<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<Section Label="sec:new1.1">
<Heading>What's New in Version 1.1?</Heading>

First of all, of course several character tables were added; for an overview,
see the file <F>doc/ctbldiff.pdf</F> in the home directory of the package.
Also lots of class fusions were added.
This includes factor fusions onto the tables of the factor groups modulo the
largest normal <M>p</M>-subgroups whenever the tables of the factors are
available;
these maps admit the automatic construction of the <M>p</M>-modular
Brauer tables if the corresponding tables of the factors are available.
For example, the <M>2</M>-modular Brauer table of the maximal subgroup of the
type <M>2^{10}:M_{22}</M> in the group <M>Fi_{22}</M> is available
because of the known <M>2</M>-modular table of <M>M_{22}</M>
and the stored factor fusion onto the table of <M>M_{22}</M>.

<P/>

Second, more information has been made more explicit, in the following sense.

<List>
<Item>
  <Ref Attr="Identifier" BookName="ref"/> values of tables
  that are constructed from generic tables are now valid arguments of
  <Ref Func="CharacterTable" BookName="ref"/>,
  for example <C>CharacterTable( "C10" )</C>
  and <C>CharacterTable( "Sym(5)" )</C>
  can be used to create the character table of the cyclic group of order
  <M>10</M> and of the symmetric group of degree <M>5</M>, respectively.
</Item>
<Item>
  Attributes have been introduced that replace more or less hidden
  components (see&nbsp;<Ref Sect="sec:access"/>);
  in particular, the way how many ordinary tables are encoded
  via the construction from other tables is no longer encapsulated
  in a function call but instead the name of the function and the
  arguments are stored as an attribute value
  (see&nbsp;<Ref Func="ConstructionInfoCharacterTable"/>).
</Item>
<Item>
  The functions that are used for the table constructions have been
  documented (see Chapter&nbsp;<Ref Chap="chap:constructions"/>).
</Item>
<Item>
  Several consistency checks are now part of the package distribution,
  in the files <F>gap4/test.gd</F> and <F>gap4/test.gi</F>.
  However, currently they are not documented.
  The new file <F>tst/testall.g</F> lists the files that belong to the
  <Q>standard test suite</Q>.
  Further checks involving the &GAP; Character Table Library are parts
  of the &GAP; packages AtlasRep (see&nbsp;<Cite Key="AtlasRep"/>) and TomLib.
</Item>
<Item>
  As a part of the consistency checks, class fusions between character
  tables and from character tables into corresponding tables of marks
  have been recomputed, and the <C>text</C> components have been standardized;
  this means that the texts express whether the maps are unique, unique
  up to table automorphisms, or ambiguous.
  However, currently this is not documented.
</Item>
<Item>
  One can now avoid unloading the contents of data files, which can speed
  up computations involving many library tables
  (see&nbsp;<Ref Func="CTblLibSetUnload"/>).
</Item>
</List>

<P/>

Third, several errors have been corrected
(again see&nbsp;<F>doc/ctbldiff.pdf</F>).
Most of them affect class fusions, and for most of those, the term error
could be regarded as not really appropriate.
The point is that there are class fusions which predate the availability of
Brauer tables in the Character Table Library (in fact many of them have been
inherited from the library of the &CAS; system),
but they are not compatible with the Brauer tables.
For example, there are four possible class fusion from <M>M_{23}</M> into <M>Co_3</M>,
which lie in one orbit under the relevant groups of table automorphisms;
two of these maps are not compatible with the <M>3</M>-modular Brauer tables of
<M>M_{23}</M> and <M>Co_3</M>, and unfortunately the class fusion that was stored on
the &CAS; tables --and that was available in version&nbsp;1.0 of the &GAP;
Character Table Library-- was one of the not compatible maps.
One could argue that the class fusion has older rights,
and that the Brauer tables should be adjusted to them, but the Brauer tables
are published in the &ATLAS; of Brauer Characters&nbsp;<Cite Key="JLPW95"/>,
which is an accepted standard.

<P/>

Finally, the &GAP; functions for reading and writing other formats of
character tables have been moved here from the main &GAP; library
(see Chapter&nbsp;<Ref Chap="chap:interfaces"/>),
because they are useful only for library tables.
The &GAP;&nbsp;3 format is now also supported, mainly for documentation
purposes (see Section&nbsp;<Ref Sect="sec:interface-gap3"/>).

</Section>


<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<Section Label="sec:acknowledgments">
<Heading>Acknowledgements</Heading>

The functions for the conversion of &CAS; tables
to &GAP; format have been written by Götz Pfeiffer.
The functions for converting the <Q>Cambridge format</Q>
(in which the original data of the &ATLAS; of Finite Groups had been stored)
to &GAP; format have been written by Christoph Jansen.

<P/>

The development of the &GAP; Character Table Library has been supported
by several DFG grants,
in particular the project
<Q>Representation Theory of Finite Groups and Finite Dimensional Algebras</Q>
(until 1991),
and the Schwerpunkt <Q>Algorithmische Zahlentheorie und Algebra</Q>
(from 1991 until 1997).

<P/>

Thanks to Frank Lübeck and Max Neunhöffer for
their help with solving technical problems concerning the HMTL part of the
example files that belong to the package documentation,
and to Ian Hutchinson whose &TeX; to HTML translator <C>TtH</C> was used to
provide these HTML files.

<P/>

The functions <Ref Func="DeligneLusztigName"/>,
<Ref Func="DeligneLusztigNames"/>, and <Ref Func="UnipotentCharacter"/>,
as well as the corresponding data for the finite groups of Lie type
in the &GAP; Character Table Library
(see Section&nbsp;<Ref Sect="sec:unipotsec"/>)
have been contributed by Michael Claßen-Houben, see&nbsp;<Cite Key="Cla05"/>.

<P/>

Several newly added character tables have been computed by Sebastian Dany,
see&nbsp;<Cite Key="Dan06"/>.
<!-- now complete: maxes of 2.A5, A9, 2.A9, A10, 2.A10, ... -->

</Section>
</Chapter>

<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->

