<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<!-- % -->
<!-- %A about.tex           GAP documentation -->
<!-- % -->
<!-- %A @(#)<M>Id: about.tex,v 4.7 2001/06/11 14:07:59 gap Exp </M> -->
<!-- % -->
<!-- %Y Copyright 1990-1992, Lehrstuhl D für Mathematik, RWTH Aachen, Germany -->
<!-- % -->
<Chapter Label="About the GAP Reference Manual">
<Heading>About the GAP Reference Manual</Heading>

This is one of two manuals documenting the core part of &GAP;,
the other being the <E>&GAP; Tutorial</E>
<Alt Only="HTML">(see <Ref BookName="tut" Label="Preface"/>)</Alt>.
<P/>
This manual, the <E>&GAP; reference manual</E> contains the official definitions
of &GAP; functions. It should give all information to someone who wants to
use &GAP; as it is. It is not intended to be read cover-to-cover.
<P/>
This manual is divided into chapters, sections and subsections.
Chapter&nbsp;<Ref Chap="The Help System"/> describes the <E>help system</E>,
which provides access to all  manuals from a running &GAP; session.
Chapter&nbsp;<Ref Chap="Running GAP"/> gives technical advice for <E>running</E> &GAP;.
Chapter&nbsp;<Ref Chap="The Programming Language"/> introduces the &GAP; language,
while the next chapters deal with the <E>environment</E>
provided by &GAP; for the user.
These are followed by the main bulk of chapters
which is devoted to various mathematical structures that &GAP; can handle.
<P/>
To get started a new user may first look at parts of the Tutorial. 
<P/>
A &GAP; installation also contains a number of <E>&GAP; packages</E>
which are developed independently of the core part of &GAP; and can be loaded
into a &GAP; session. Each package comes with a separate manual which is 
also available from the &GAP; help system.
<P/>

<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<Section Label="Credit">
<Heading>Credit</Heading>

The manual tries to give credit to designers and implementors of major parts
of &GAP;. For many parts of  the &GAP; code it is  impossible to give
detailed credit, because over the time of its  development many persons have
contributed from first ideas,
even in prerunners of &GAP; such as <Package>CAS</Package> or
<Package>SOGOS</Package>, via first  implementations, improvements,
and even  total reimplementations.
The documentation of the code gives further details, but
again, it suffers from the same problem.  We  have attempted to give
attributions with the different chapters of   the manual where this seemed
to be possible, but  we  apologise for all (unavoidable) shortcomings of
this attempt.

</Section>
</Chapter>


<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %E -->

