<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %W  copyrigh.xml              GAP documentation                      LDFM -->
<!-- %W                                                                 & SMCS -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %H  @(#)<M>Id: copyrigh.msk,v 1.6 2004/02/13 17:38:52 gap Exp </M> -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %Y  Copyright 1997,  Lehrstuhl D für Mathematik,   RWTH Aachen, Germany -->
<!-- %Y  Copyright (C) 2002, The GAP Group -->
<!-- %% -->


Copyright &copyright; (1987-&RELEASEYEAR;) by the &GAP; Group, 
<P/>
incorporating the Copyright &copyright; 1999, 2000  by
        School of Mathematical and Computational Sciences,
        University of St&nbsp;Andrews,
        North Haugh, St&nbsp;Andrews, Fife KY16 9SS, Scotland
<P/>
being the Copyright &copyright; 1992 by
        Lehrstuhl D für Mathematik, RWTH,
        52056 Aachen, Germany,
transferred to St&nbsp;Andrews on July 21st, 1997.
<P/>
except for files in the distribution, which have an explicit different
copyright statement. In particular, the copyright of packages distributed
with &GAP; is usually with the package authors or their institutions.
<P/>
<P/>
<P/>
&GAP; is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
(at your option) any later version. For details, see 
the file <F>GPL</F> in the <F>etc</F> directory of the &GAP; distribution or see
<URL>http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html</URL>.
<P/>
If you obtain &GAP; please send us  a short notice to that effect, e.g.,
an  e-mail  message   to  the  address  <Email>support@gap-system.org</Email>,
containing your full  name and address.  This  allows us to keep track of
the number of &GAP; users.
<P/>
If you  publish  a mathematical  result  that  was  partly obtained using
&GAP;, please cite &GAP;, just as you would cite another paper that you
used (see below for sample citation). Also   we would appreciate if you
could inform us  about such a paper.
<P/>
Specifically, please refer to
<P/>
<Log>
[GAP] The GAP Group, GAP - Groups, Algorithms, and Programming,
      Version &VERSIONNUMBER;; &RELEASEYEAR;      (http://www.gap-system.org)
</Log>
<P/>
&GAP; is distributed by us without any warranty, to the extent permitted
by applicable state law.  We  distribute &GAP; <E>as is</E> without  warranty
of any kind, either expressed or implied, including,  but not limited to,
the implied  warranties  of merchantability and  fitness for a particular
purpose.
<P/>
The entire risk as to the quality and performance of the program is  with
you.  Should &GAP; prove defective, you assume the cost of all necessary
servicing, repair or correction.
<P/>
In no  case  unless  required by applicable law will we, and/or any other
party who  may  modify  and  redistribute  &GAP;  as permitted above, be
liable  to you for damages, including lost profits, lost monies or  other
special, incidental or consequential damages  arising out  of the  use or
inability to use &GAP;.
<P/>
You  are permitted  to modify and  redistribute  &GAP;,  but you are not
allowed  to restrict further redistribution.  That is to say  proprietary
modifications will  not  be allowed.  We want all  versions  of &GAP; to
remain free.
<P/>
If you  modify any part of &GAP; and redistribute it,  you must supply a
<F>README</F>  document.   This should specify what modifications you made  in
which  files.  We do  not  want  to take  credit  or  be blamed  for your
modifications.
<P/>
Of course we are interested in all of your modifications.  In  particular
we would like to see bug-fixes, improvements and new functions.  So again
we would appreciate it if you would inform us about all modifications you
make.


<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %E -->

