<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %W  gappkg.msk                GAP documentation             Werner Nickel -->
<!-- %W                                                       Alexander Hulpke -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %H  @(#)<M>Id: gappkg.msk,v 1.18 2004/01/26 10:09:20 gap Exp </M> -->
<!-- %% -->
<P/>
<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<Chapter Label="GAP Packages">
<Heading>GAP Packages</Heading>

<Index>package</Index>
The  functionality  of  &GAP;  can  be  extended  by  loading  &GAP;
packages. Many packages are distributed  together with the core system
of &GAP; consisting of the &GAP;  kernel, the &GAP; library and the
various data libraries.
<P/>
&GAP; packages are written by (groups  of) &GAP; users which may not
be  members  of the  &GAP;  developer  team. The  responsibility  and
copyright of a &GAP; package remains with the original author(s).
<P/>
&GAP;  packages  have  their  own  documentation  which  is  smoothly
integrated into the &GAP; help system.
<P/>
All  &GAP;  users   who  develop  new  code  are   invited  to  share
the  results  of their  efforts  with  other  &GAP; users  by  making
the  code  and its  documentation  available  in  form of  a  package.
Information how  to do  this is  available from  the &GAP;  Web pages
(<URL>http://www.gap-system.org</URL>)
and in Chapter <Ref Chap="Writing a GAP Package"/>.
There  are  possibilities  to get  a  package  distributed together  with
&GAP;  and it  is possible  to submit  a package  to a formal refereeing
process.
<P/>
In this Chapter we describe how to use existing packages.


<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<Section Label="Installing a GAP Package">
<Heading>Installing a GAP Package</Heading>

Before a  package can be  used it must  be installed. With  a standard
installation of  &GAP; there should  be quite a few  packages already
available. But since &GAP; packages are released independently of the
main  &GAP; system  it  may be  sensible to  upgrade  or install  new
packages between  upgrades of your &GAP; installation.
<P/>
A package consists of a collection  of files within a single directory
that must  be a subdirectory of  the <F>pkg</F>  directory   in one  of the
&GAP; root directories, see <Ref Sect="GAP Root Directory"/>. (If you don't
have access  to the <F>pkg</F>  directory in your main  &GAP; installation
you can add private root directories as explained in that section.)
<P/>
Whenever  you  get from  somewhere  an  archive  of a  &GAP;  package
it  should be  accompanied  with  a <F>README</F>  file  that explains  its
installation.  Some packages  just  consist  of  &GAP;  code and  the
installation  is  done  by  unpacking   the  archive  in  one  of  the
places  described above.  There are  also packages  that need  further
installation steps,  there may be  for example some  external programs
which  have  to  be  compiled  (this is  often  done  by  just  saying
<C>./configure; make</C>  inside the unpacked package  directory, but check
the individual <F>README</F> files).

</Section>


<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<Section Label="Loading a GAP Package">
<Heading>Loading a GAP Package</Heading>

<Index>automatic loading of GAP packages</Index>
<Index>disable automatic loading</Index>
Some &GAP; packages are prepared for <E>automatic loading</E>,
that is they will be loaded automatically with &GAP;,
others must in each case be separately loaded by a call to
<Ref Func="LoadPackage"/>.

<#Include Label="LoadPackage">

</Section>


<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<Section Label="Functions for GAP Packages">
<Heading>Functions for GAP Packages</Heading>

The  following functions  are  mainly  used in  files  contained in  a
package and not by users of a package.

<#Include Label="ReadPackage">
<#Include Label="TestPackageAvailability">
<#Include Label="InstalledPackageVersion">
<#Include Label="DirectoriesPackageLibrary">
<#Include Label="DirectoriesPackagePrograms">
<#Include Label="CompareVersionNumbers">

</Section>
</Chapter>


<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %E -->

