<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %W  preface.tex               GAP documentation         Joachim Neubueser -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %H  @(#)<M>Id: preface.tex,v 4.44 2006/06/27 21:37:08 gap Exp </M> -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %Y  Copyright (C) 1997, Lehrstuhl D für Mathematik, RWTH Aachen, Germany -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %%  This file contains the preface of the GAP reference manual. -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->

<Chapter Label="Preface">
<Heading>Preface</Heading>

Welcome to &GAP;. This preface serves not only to introduce 
<Q>the &GAP; Reference Manual</Q>, but also as an introduction to the
system as a whole.
<P/>
&GAP; stands  for  <E>Groups, Algorithms  and Programming</E>.  The  name was
chosen to reflect  the aim of  the  system, which  is introduced in  this
reference manual.  Since  that  choice,  the  system has become   somewhat
broader,    and  you will  also   find information   about algorithms and
programming  for other   algebraic structures,   such as semigroups   and
algebras.
<P/>
In addition to this manual, there is the <Q>&GAP; Tutorial</Q> 
<Alt Only="HTML">(see <Ref BookName="tut" Label="Preface"/>)</Alt>.
A lot of the functionality of the system and a number of
contributed extensions are provided as <Q>&GAP; packages</Q>
and each of these has its own manual.
This preface, however, serves as an introduction to the whole system.
<P/>
Subsequent sections of this preface explain the structure of the
system and the arrangements for the attribution of credit for
authorship and maintenance of the system; acknowledge those who have
made particular contributions to this and previous releases and
outline the changes from earlier versions.
<P/>

<!-- TEMPORARY PREFACE FOR GAP 4.5 BETA FOR PACKAGE AUTHORS -->

<Section Label="GAP 4.5.2 (beta) preface">
<Heading>Preface for the second beta Release of &GAP; 4.5.2 (beta)</Heading>

<E>
This is a temporary preface for the second beta release of &GAP; 4.5 for the package
authors. The rest of the preface will be revised an updated later before the
first public release of &GAP; 4.5.
</E>
<P/>

<E>Dear authors of &GAP; packages,</E>
<P/>

There have been many changes in the development version of &GAP; 
during almost three years since the release of &GAP;&nbsp;4.4.12. Some
major developments that were started earlier are now ready for release and it's
now high time for the &GAP;&nbsp;4.5 release, which we plan to have in November 
2011.
<P/>

Earlier in April 2011 we made available the first beta release of &GAP;&nbsp;4.5,
and we appreciate all feedback we received from package authors and users. 
Moreover, in the subsequent period some packages already have been upgraded to 
work with &GAP;&nbsp;4.5. 
Now, to allow you to test your packages with the new features and make the 
final step towards the official release of &GAP;&nbsp;4.5,
we have prepared the second beta version of &GAP;&nbsp;4.5, named 
&GAP;&nbsp;4.5.2, which is available to package authors in the following directory:
<P/>
<URL>ftp://ftp.gap-system.org/pub/gap/gap45/beta/</URL>
<P/>

The archive you will find to download at the above URL is not quite the same 
as the &GAP;&nbsp;4.4 archives. For the general release of &GAP;&nbsp;4.5 
(and subsequent updates) we plan the main form of distribution of &GAP; 
to be a single dated archive file including current versions of 
all packages at that date and binaries for the most common 
environments (Windows, MacOS, and Linux on 32 and 64 bit intel processors). 
We plan that these archives will be rebuilt and marked with a new timestamp
whenever a new version of a package is released, which we expect to be quite 
frequently and we will make no special distinction between 
updates to packages and to the core system. For the beta release, however,
we do not quite have the setup for this fully in place. 
The beta archives will include packages, but not binaries.
<P/>

Please download and install &GAP;&nbsp;4.5.2 and test it with your package(s). 
Since we have not yet included binaries, you will need to compile the 
&GAP; kernel as usual. To run &GAP; under
Windows, you may either compile it yourself with Cygwin or write to Alexander 
Konovalov (<C>alexk@mcs.st-andrews.ac.uk</C>) and ask him to send you the &GAP; 
executable file for Windows.
<P/>

If you have a new version of your package that you would like to release with the first
public release of &GAP;&nbsp;4.5, please prepare the new version of your package 
before November 15th 2011. When you've done that, please make the new version available 
to us for testing and notify Alexander Konovalov (<C>alexk@mcs.st-andrews.ac.uk</C>)
about the location of the relevant <File>PackageInfo.g</File> file
to arrange for the &GAP; Group to obtain your package for further tests.
<P/>

Note that if the new version of your package is compatible with both &GAP;&nbsp;4.4
and &GAP;&nbsp;4.5 you need not to change its location. However, if the new version
will require &GAP;&nbsp;4.5, please put in under different URL so it will not be
picked up by the package update scripts for &GAP;&nbsp;4.4 which we will still 
continue to run until the official release of  &GAP;&nbsp;4.5.
<P/>

If a package is released to us later than November 15th 2011 and our testing shows any 
problems (most likely in interactions with other packages) we may not be able to 
sort them out in time to include it in the first official release of &GAP;&nbsp;4.5. 
<P/>

We have already tested most of the current versions of &GAP; packages with the
beta-release of &GAP;&nbsp;4.5, and did not find any serious problems. Thus, we hope
that for most packages the change will go smoothly - a version of the
package with basic compatibility with &GAP;&nbsp;4.5 can be produced with little or no
effort (for most packages simply recompiling the documentation would be good
enough). We would encourage you though, to do a little more work and adjust your package 
to use some of the new features of the GAP 4.5 package interface. 
<P/>

This is especially important since some of the changes involve improvements 
to the &GAP; package interface to deal with problems which have arisen and 
cope more smoothly as the number of packages approaches~100 and the complexity 
of the functionality supplied by packages and the relationships between packages increases. 
<P/>

As well as testing your package, please let us know of any problems you find 
with &GAP;&nbsp;4.5 itself. We encourage you to test &GAP;&nbsp;4.5 on as 
many configurations as possible. We welcome all feedback to 
<C>support@gap-system.org</C> including comments, suggestions, bug 
reports and manual corrections.
<P/>

You will find a brief overview of main changes in &GAP;&nbsp;4.5 from the
package author's perspective, descriptions of known problems that we observed while
testing current packages with &GAP;&nbsp;4.5, and some further guidelines in
the Appendix of the <Package>Example</Package> package included in the second
beta release (see <Ref BookName="Example" Label="Guidelines for Writing a GAP Package"/>).
<P/>

<E>Best wishes,</E>
<P/>
<E>the GAP development team</E>
<P/>
<E>September 2011</E>
<P/>
</Section>

<!-- TEMPORARY PREFACE FOR GAP 4.5 BETA FOR PACKAGE AUTHORS ENDS HERE -->


<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<Section Label="The GAP System">
<Heading>The &GAP; System</Heading>
<#Include SYSTEM "../ref/overview.xml">
</Section>


<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<Section Label="Authorship and Maintenance">
<Heading>Authorship and Maintenance</Heading>

Previous versions of &GAP; have simply included the increasingly long
list of all of the authors of the system with no indication as to who
contributed what. With &GAP; 4.3 we have introduced a new concept:
<E>modules</E>, to allow us to report the authorship of the system in more
detail. A module is a part of &GAP; which provides identifiable
functionality and has reasonably clean interfaces with the rest of the
system (usually it consists of separate files). Each module has its
own lists of authors and maintainers, which are not necessarily the
same. A preliminary list of modules and their attributions appears in
this manual. Note that we are still in the process of identifying
modules within the system, so large parts of the system do not yet
fall into any module. Since also we all collaborate closely in
designing, developing and debugging the system, it should not be
assumed that the list of modules in this manual represents all of
everyone's contribution, or that it lists everyone who made any
contribution at all to each module.
<P/>
All &GAP; packages are also considered to be modules and have their
own authors and maintainers. It should however be noted that some
packages provide interfaces between &GAP; and an external program, a
copy of which is included for convenience, and that, in these cases,
we do not claim that the module authors or maintainers wrote, or
maintain, this external program. Similarly, some modules and packages
include large data libraries that may have been computed by many
people. We try to make clear in each case what credit is attributable
to whom.
<P/>
We have, for some time, operated a refereeing system for contributed
packages, both to ensure the quality of the software we distribute,
and to provide recognition for the authors. We now consider this to be
a refereeing system for modules, and we would note, in particular
that, although it does not use the standard package interface, the
library of small groups has been refereed and accepted on exactly the
same basis as the accepted  packages.
<P/>
We also include with this distribution a
number of packages which have not (yet) gone through our refereeing
process. Some may be accepted in the future, in other cases the
authors have chosen not to submit them.  More information can be found
on our World Wide Web site,
see section <Ref Sect="Further Information about GAP"/>.

</Section>


<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<Section Label="Acknowledgements">
<Heading>Acknowledgements</Heading>

Very many people have worked on, and contributed to, &GAP; over the
years since its inception. On our Web site you will find the prefaces
to the previous releases, each of which acknowledges people who have
made special contributions to that release. Even so, it is appropriate
to mention here Joachim Neubüser whose vision of a free,
open and extensible system for computational algebra inspired &GAP;
in the first place, and Martin Schönert, who was the
technical architect of &GAP; 3 and &GAP; 4.
<P/>
In the past years &GAP; development
has become a more and more widely distributed operation, and
increasingly dependent on hard voluntary work by developers not solely
or mainly employed to work on &GAP;. 
<P/>
Nevertheless, the development
process has remained constructive and friendly, even when wrangling
over difficult technical decisions, or sensitive questions of
attribution and credit and I must express our huge gratitude to
everyone involved for this.
<P/>
The list of modules which appears in this manual now gives a partial
idea of the contributions of different people, but we would like to
mention some people who have made important contributions to the
development process over the last years that do not show up there:
<P/>
Steve Linton has been leading the &GAP; group in St Andrews over the last
years and continues to be the main kernel maintainer and developer. The group
in St Andrews also maintains most of the development infrastructure and 
helps with user support.
<P/>
Thomas Breuer continues to develop many areas of the system, and
to play a vital role in clarifying our underlying concepts, despite
now working in industry.
<P/>
Frank Lübeck set up a new system for automatic handling of
packages and helped with various kernel issues.
<P/>
Bettina Eick and her research group in Braunschweig have contributed much
functionality, mainly in the form of packages.
<P/>
Max Neunhöffer has brought much fresh insight to bear on the
design of crucial parts of the system, and also done a lot of the
ensuing work; Stefan Kohl and Volkmar Felsch have both brought
enormous persistence to pointing out errors and inconsistencies in code and 
documentation, improving error messages and generally polishing the
system; and very many others have contributed ideas, insight and hard
work to produce this release. Senior colleagues, especially Joachim
Neubüser, Edmund Robertson, and Charley Wright, continue to
provide encouragement support and constructive criticism.

</Section>


<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<Section Label="Further Information about GAP">
<Heading>Further Information about &GAP;</Heading>
<Index Subkey="for GAP">web sites</Index>
<Index>email addresses</Index>
<Index Subkey="email address">support</Index>
<#Include SYSTEM "../ref/moreinfo.xml">
</Section>

</Chapter>


<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
<!-- %% -->
<!-- %E -->

