<Chapter Label="MPIGAP">
  <Heading>MPIGAP</Heading>

  <Section Label="MPIGAP Overview">
    <Heading>MPIGAP Overview</Heading>

MPIGAP is the library for GAP which supports distributed-memory systems. It is based on MPI communication library, and
in its base is the ParGAP package. MPIGAP and supports distributed-memory programming on different levels, from
low-level MPI bindings, to the high-level operations with implicit task management and load-balancing.

Prerequisites for installing MPIGAP are:

<Enum>
<Item>Working MPI library, with <C>mpicc</C> compiler, and <C>MPIHOME</C> environment variable set to the root directory of
the library (<C>mpicc</C> needs to be in <C>$(MPIHOME)/bin</C>. MPIGAP was tested using MPICH 3 MPI library
(www.mpich.org), but should work also with OpenMPI.
</Item>

<Item>GAP IO package, if IO Pickling is used for object marshalling. See below</Item>
</Enum>

Once the prerequisites are satisfied, you can install MPIGAP by checking out the latest hpcgap repository and then, from
the GAP root directory, doing

<Example><![CDATA[
./make.hpc mpi
]]></Example>

Once MPIGAP is build, you can run it with

<Example><![CDATA[
mpiexec -n <noProcesses> bin/<arch>/gap
]]></Example>

Probably the best way to run MPIGAP programs is in batch mode. To run your inputFile.g in this way, do

<Example><![CDATA[
mpiexec -n <noProcesses> bin/<arch>/gap inputFile.g
]]></Example>

  </Section>

  <Section Label="Object Marshalling">
    <Heading>Object Marshalling</Heading>

In MPIGAP, it is necessary to have a mechanism for transferring objects between different MPI nodes. This requires
functions to convert a GAP object into its binary or string representation, and to convert this representation into a
GAP object. This is called object marshalling. Currently, MPIGAP supports two mechanisms for object marshalling:

<Enum>
<Item> Object serialisation via <C>SerializeToNativeString</C> and <C>DeserializeNativeString</C>. This method of
marshalling is much faster of the two, but also has some drawbacks. It is not portable, and therefore cannot be used
when MPI nodes have different architecture. Also, the range of object that can be marshalled in this way is smaller than
with IO Pickling. For example, functions cannot be marshalled in this way.</Item>

<Item>IO pickling via <C>IO_Pickle</C> and <C>IO_Unpickle</C>. This marshalling method requires <C>IO</C> package to be
installed. Compared to object serialization, marshalling object using this method is much slower, up to the point where
its performance becomes unacceptable for larger objects (e.g. large matrices). However, it is portable and many more
objects (including functions) have pickling methods implemented.
</Item>
</Enum>

The default marshalling method is object serialization. User can change the method used by setting the
<C>MPIGAP_MARSHALLING</C> variable to <C>"Serialize"</C> or <C>"Pickle"</C> in her init file.

Most of the time, object marshalling is hidden from the user. The user needs to worry about it only if in her
application, some &quot;unusual&quot; objects need to be transferred between nodes, and no serialization method for
these objects is written, or if executing GAP in a distributed systems where different nodes have different
architecture. Also, user needs to use explicit marshalling when programming using low-level MPI bindings (see below).
For vast majority of cases, the default marshalling option works and gives very good performance.

  </Section>
  <Section Label="Distributed Task Management">
    <Heading>Distributed Task Management</Heading>

MPIGAP has distributed implementation of most of the primitves related to the task management in shared memory. API for
distributed versions of these primitives is almost identical to their shared-memory version, with the exception of
denoting functions if object serialisation is used as a method of object marshalling.

    <Subsection Label="CreateTask">
      <Heading>CreateTask(listOfArguments)</Heading>

<C>CreateTask</C> creates a task, using <C>listOfArguments</C> for task function and arguments. The operation returns
the created task.  The first element of <C>listOfArguments</C> is a function or a function name, and the remaining
elements are arguments. <C>CreateTask</C> just creates a task, and does not put it in the task queue nor does it execute
it. To do this, user needs to call <C>ExecuteTask</C>.

If the serialisation method is used for object marshalling, then the first element of <C>listOfArguments</C> needs to be
a string denoting function name, and the function needs to be declared and installed using <C>DeclareGlobalFunction</C>
and <C>InstallGlobalFunction</C>. In the case when pickling is used for object marshalling, first element of
<C>listOfArguments</C> can also be a function.

    </Subsection>
    <Subsection Label="ExecuteTask">
      <Heading>ExecuteTask(task)</Heading>

<C>ExecuteTask</C> puts <C>task</C> into the task queue of the node where it was created.

If work-stealing is enabled (see <C>StartStealing</C> and <C>StopStealing</C> below), the task can be stolen by a remote
node. All of the arguments are copied to the remote node. One or more arguments can be global object handles. In this
case, only the handles (and not the underlying objects) are copied to the remote node.

    </Subsection>
    <Subsection Label="RunTask">
      <Heading>RunTask(f,arg1,arg2,...,argN)</Heading>

<C>RunTask</C> creates a task, with the function (or function name, depending on the method for marshalling, see
<C>CreateTask</C>) <C>f</C> and the arguments <C>arg1</C>, <C>arg2</C>, ..., <C>argN</C> and puts it in the task queue
of the node where it is created.

If work-stealing is enabled (see <C>StartStealing</C> and <C>StopStealing</C> below), the task can be stolen by a remote
node. All of the arguments are copied to the remote node. One or more arguments can be global object handles. In this
case, only the handles (and not the underlying objects) are copied to the remote node.

    </Subsection>
    <Subsection Label="SendTask">
      <Heading>SendTask(t,node)</Heading>

<C>SendTask(t,node)</C> sends the task for the execution on MPI node <C>node</C>. Task arguments are copied to the
destination node. If argument to the task is handle, only the handle (and not the object it points to) is copied. On the
destination node, the object needs to be fetched (via <C>RemotePullObj</C> or <C>RemoteCloneObj</C>), or, alternatively,
it needs to be explicitly pushed from the node calling <C>SendTask</C> via <C>RemoteCopyObj</C> or <C>RemotePushObj</C>.

    </Subsection>
    <Subsection Label="StartStealing">
      <Heading>StartStealing()</Heading>

<C>StartStealing</C> enables work-stealing (disabled by default). Once the work-stealing is enabled, the nodes can steal
tasks from each others&#39; task queues. If work-stealing is disabled, the only way of transfering tasks between
different nodes is using <C>SendTask</C> operation.

    </Subsection>
    <Subsection Label="StopStealing">
      <Heading>StopStealing()</Heading>

<C>StopStealing</C> disabless work-stealing (this is the default option). Once the work-stealing is disabled, the only
way of transfering tasks between different nodes is using <C>SendTask</C> operation.
    </Subsection>
  </Section>
    <Section Label="Global Objects and Handles">
    <Heading>Global Objects and Handles</Heading>

Global objects are objects that can be accessed from multiple distributed nodes. They are accessed via object handles
that represent global pointers to these objects. The same object handle can exist on multiple nodes, pointing to the
same global object. Handles can be used to migrate, copy and change objects they point to.

Global object handles represent pointers to global objects. The same handle can live on different nodes. Furthermore, it
is possible for handles to keep cached copy of the global object on a local node.

The type of a handle determines the operations that are allowed with the object they point to. There are three types of
handles:

<List>
<Item> A read-only handle is a handle to an object that can be read only. Since the object that a read-only handle points to
cannot be changed, this object can freely be moved and copied between nodes (via <C>RemoteCopyObj</C>,
<C>RemoteCloneObj</C>, <C>RemotePushObj</C> and  <C>RemotePullObj</C>, see below). However, changing the object that
such handle points to (via <C>SetByHandle</C>, see below) is not allowed.</Item>

<Item> A read-write Handle is a handle to an object that can be read and   modified. To ensure consistency in accessing this
object, MPIGAP ensures that only one copy of the object exists, which means that  copying of such object between nodes
(via <C>RemoteCopyObj</C> and  <C>RemoteCloneObj</C>) is not allowed, and will result in an error. Moving the object
between nodes (via <C>RemotePushObj</C> and <C>RemotePullObj</C>) is allowed, and so is changing the object (via
<C>SetByHandle</C>).</Item>

<Item> A volatile handle is a handle to an object that can be freely moved, copied and changed. This means that the
consistency of such object on multiple nodes in not guaranteed, and the same global handle on multiple nodes can point
to different objects.</Item>
</List>

  <Subsection Label="CreateHandleFromObj">
    <Heading>CreateHandleFromObj(obj [, access_type])</Heading>

<C>CreateHandleFromObj</C> takes an object <C>obj</C> and creates a handle for accessing that object. <C>access_type</C>
can be one of the constants <C>ACCESS_TYPES.READ_ONLY</C>, <C>ACCESS_TYPES.READ_WRITE</C> or
<C>ACCESS_TYPES.VOLATILE</C>. If <C>access_type</C> is not provided, the default access type is
<C>ACCESS_TYPES.READ_ONLY</C>. Note that setting a handle to read-only also makes the underlying object immutable.

When a handle for a boxed object (anything other than small integer or finite field element) is created, the object is
automatically put in shared region, so for all future accesses to that object a lock needs to be obtained.

Examples:

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> x := [1,2,3,4,5];;
gap> handle := CreateHandleFromObj(x);;
]]></Example>

creates a read-only handle for the list <C>x</C>, making the list immutable in turn.

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> x := 42;;
gap> handle := CreateHandleFromObj(x,ACCESS_TYPES.READ_WRITE);;
]]></Example>

creates a read-write handle for the integer object. The integer is copied into the handle, and can be changed via
<C>SetByHandle</C> and <C>GetByHandle</C> (see below), not via changes to the variable <C>x</C>:

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> Open(handle);
gap> GetHandleObj(handle);
42
gap> x := 51;;
gap> GetHandleObj(handle);
42
gap> SetByHandle(handle, 20);
gap> GetHandleObj(handle);
20
]]></Example>

  </Subsection>
  <Subsection Label="GetHandleAccessType">
    <Heading>GetHandleAccessType(handle)</Heading>

<C>GetHandleAccessType</C> returns the access type of a handle.

  </Subsection>
  <Subsection Label="Open">
    <Heading>Open(handle)</Heading>

Each thread that wants to use a handle in any way needs to explicitly open it. This is for the purpose of explicit
reference counting, so that the handles that are not used by any thread can be garbage collected. <C>Open</C> opens a
handle in the thread that calls it.

  </Subsection>
  <Subsection Label="Close">
    <Heading>Close(handle)</Heading>

<C>Close</C> closes a handle in the thread that calls it, decreasing reference count for that handle in turn. All
subsequent operations on that handle in the thread that called <C>Close</C> result in an error, unless the handle is
open again.

  </Subsection>
  <Subsection Label="Destory">
    <Heading>Destory(handle)</Heading>

<C>Destroy</C> destroyes a handle on the node that calls it, meaning that all subsequent operations on that handle on
that node result in an error, and that the handle cannot be reopened. This also makes the object to which the handle
points to available for garbage collection on that node. Note that the same handle (with the accompanying object) can
still exist on other nodes.

The handle is destroyed only if it is safe, i.e. if all of the threads on the node that calls <C>Destroy</C> have closed
the handle and, in the case the handle is read-write and it holds the actual object, all nodes that the handle was sent
to also destroyed their copies of it.

  </Subsection>
  <Subsection Label="GetHandeObj">
    <Heading>GetHandeObj(handle)</Heading>

<C>GetHandleObj</C> returns the object that a handle points to. If the object that a handle points to is on some remote
node, the call will block until the object is fetched.

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> handle := CreateHandleFromObj ( [1,2,3,4,5] );;
gap> Open(handle);
gap> GetHandleFromObj(handle);
[1,2,3,4,5]
]]></Example>

  </Subsection>
  <Subsection Label="SendHandle">
    <Heading>SendHandle(handle, node)</Heading>

<C>SendHandle</C> sends handle <C>handle</C> to a destination MPI node <C>node</C>. Note that only the handle itself
(and not the object it points to) is sent.

  </Subsection>
  <Subsection Label="RemoteCopyObj">
    <Heading>RemoteCopyObj(handle, node)</Heading>

<C>RemoteCopyObj</C> copies the object that <C>handle</C> points to to the <C>node</C> MPI node. <C>handle</C> must have
read-write or volatile access type. Note that the handle may or may not exists on the destination node. If it does
exist, the object it points to on the receiving node (if any) is overwritten by the object that is sent. If the handle
does not exist, it is first sent to the receiving node. Therefore, the following two pieces of code produce the same
result:

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> handle := CreateHandleFromObj ([1,2,3,4,5]);
gap> RemoteCopyObj (handle, 1);
]]></Example>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> handle := CreateHandleFromObj ([1,2,3,4,5]);
gap> SendHandle (handle, 1);
gap> RemoteCopyObj (handle, 1);
]]></Example>

  </Subsection>
  <Subsection Label="RemotePushObj">
    <Heading>RemotePushObj(handle, node)</Heading>

<C>RemotePushObj</C> migrates the object that <C>handle</C> points to to the <C>node</C> MPI node. It can be called for
all types of handles (read-only, read-write and volatile). Note that the handle may or may not exists on the destination
node. If it does exist, the object it points to on the receiving node (if any) is overwritten by the object that is
sent. If the handle does not exist, it is first sent to the receiving node. Therefore, the following two pieces of code
produce the same result:

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> handle := CreateHandleFromObj ([1,2,3,4,5]);
gap> RemotePushObj (handle, 1);
]]></Example>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> handle := CreateHandleFromObj ([1,2,3,4,5]);
gap> SendHandle (handle, 1);
gap> RemotePushObj (handle, 1);
]]></Example>

  </Subsection>
  <Subsection Label="RemotePullObj">
    <Heading>RemotePullObj(handle)</Heading>

<C>RemotePullObj</C> fetches the object that <C>handle</C> points to and stores it on the node that called the function.
The object is deleted from the node that owns it. This operation can be called for all types of handles.

The following piece of code creates a handle for a list, pushes the list to the node 1 and then fetches it back,
deleting it from node 1.

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> handle := CreateHandleFromObj ([1,2,3,4,5]);
gap> RemotePushObj (handle, 1);
gap> RemotePullObj (handle);
]]></Example>

  </Subsection>
  <Subsection Label="RemoteCloneObj">
    <Heading>RemoteCloneObj(handle)</Heading>

<C>RemotePullObj</C> fetches the object that <C>handle</C> points to and stores it on the node that called the function.
The object also remains on the node which originally owned it.  This operation can be called for read-only and volatile
handles.

The following piece of code creates a handle for a list, pushes the list to the node 1 and then fetches it back, while
still retaining its copy on node 1.

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> handle := CreateHandleFromObj ([1,2,3,4,5]);
gap> RemotePushObj (handle, 1);
gap> RemoteCloneObj (handle);
]]></Example>

  </Subsection>
  </Section>

  <Section Label="Low-level MPI Bindings">
    <Heading>Low-level MPI Bindings</Heading>

These primitives provide the functionality similar to the C MPI bindings. They have the same name as their C
counterparts, with somewhat simpler interface. All of these functions deal with &#39;raw&#39; data (i.e. they assume
that GAP objects that are transferred between MPI nodes are already marshalled to strings), and should only be used if
higher-level models (tasks, global objects, distributed data structures and skeletons) are not sufficient or do not give
acceptable performance.

    <Subsection Label="MPI_Comm_size">
      <Heading>MPI_Comm_size() </Heading>

Returns the number of MPI nodes in the application.

    </Subsection>
    <Subsection Label="MPI_Comm_rank">
      <Heading>MPI_Comm_rank()</Heading>

Returns the rank of the MPI node that is calling it. The rank is between 0 and <C>MPI_Comm_size()</C>-1.

    </Subsection>
    <Subsection Label="MPI_Get_count">
      <Heading>MPI_Get_count()</Heading>

Returns the size (in bytes) of the last received message on this node.

    </Subsection>
    <Subsection Label="MPI_Get_source">
      <Heading>MPI_Get_source()</Heading>

Returns the rank of the sender node of the last received message.

    </Subsection>
    <Subsection Label="MPI_Get_tag">
      <Heading>MPI_Get_tag()</Heading>

Returns the tag of the last received message.

    </Subsection>
    <Subsection Label="MPI_Send">
      <Heading>MPI_Send(message, destination[, tag])</Heading>

Sends the message to the destination node. <C>message</C> is a string containing the message to be sent,
<C>destination</C> is a rank of the receiving process, and <C>tag</C> is an optional integer parameter specifying the
tag of the message (which can be retreived on the destination process by <C>MPI_Get_tag()</C>.

    </Subsection>
    <Subsection Label="MPI_Recv">
      <Heading>MPI_Recv(message[, source, tag])</Heading>

Receives the message and puts it into <C>message</C> string buffer.  If <C>source</C> is specified, only message from
that MPI node is received. If <C>tag</C> is specified, only the message with that tag is received.

    </Subsection>
    <Subsection Label="MPI_Probe">
      <Heading>MPI_Probe()</Heading>

Blocking probe for a message. The call returns when a new message is available, and the message can be received with
<C>MPI_Recv</C>.

    </Subsection>
    <Subsection Label="MPI_Iprobe">
      <Heading>MPI_Iprobe()</Heading>

Non-blocking probe for a message. The call returns true if a new message is available for receiving (via
<C>MPI_Recv</C>), and false otherwise.

    </Subsection>
  </Section>
</Chapter>
