<Chapter Label="Tasks">
  <Heading>Tasks</Heading>
  <Section Label="Overview">
    <Heading>Overview</Heading>

    Tasks provide mid- to high-level functionality for programmers to describe asynchronous workflows. A task is an
    asynchronously or synchronously executing job; functions exist to create tasks that are executed concurrently, on
    demand, or in the current thread; to wait for their completion, check their status, and retrieve any results.
    <P/>
    Here is a simple example of sorting a list in the background:

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> task := RunTask(x -> SortedList(x), [3,2,1]);;
gap> WaitTask(task);
gap> TaskResult(task);
[ 1, 2, 3 ]
]]></Example>

<Ref Func="RunTask"/> dispatches a task to run in the background; a task is described by a function and zero or more
arguments that are passed to <Ref Func="RunTask"/>. <Ref Func="WaitTask"/> waits for the task to complete; and
<C>TaskResult</C> returns the result of the task.
<P/>
<Ref Func="TaskResult"/> does an implicit <Ref Func="WaitTask"/>, so the second line above can actually be omitted:

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> task := RunTask(x -> SortedList(x), [3,2,1]);;
gap> TaskResult(task);
[ 1, 2, 3 ]
]]></Example>

It is simple to run two tasks in parallel. Let&#39;s compute the factorial of 10000 by splitting the work between two
tasks:

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> task1 := RunTask(Product, [1..5000]);;
gap> task2 := RunTask(Product, [5001..10000]);;
gap> TaskResult(task1) * TaskResult(task2) = Factorial(10000);
true
]]></Example>

You can use <Ref Func="DelayTask"/> to delay executing the task until its result is actually needed.

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> task1 := DelayTask(Product, [1..5000]);;
gap> task2 := DelayTask(Product, [5001..10000]);;
gap> WaitTask(task1, task2);
gap> TaskResult(task1) * TaskResult(task2) = Factorial(10000);
true
]]></Example>

Note that <Ref Func="WaitTask"/> is used here to start execution of both tasks; otherwise, <C>task2</C> would not be
started until <C>TaskResult(task1)</C> has been evaluated.
<P/>
To start execution of a delayed task, you can also use <C>ExecuteTask</C>. This has no effect if a task has already been
running.
<P/>
For convenience, you can also use <Ref Func="ImmediateTask"/> to execute a task synchronously (i.e., the task is started
immediately and the call does not return until the task has completed).

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> task := ImmediateTask(x -> SortedList(x), [3,2,1]);;
gap> TaskResult(task);
[ 1, 2, 3 ]
]]></Example>

This is indistinguishable from calling the function directly, but provides the same interface as normal tasks.
<P/>
Sometimes it can be useful to ignore the result of a task. The <C>RunAsyncTask</C> provides the necessary functionality.

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> RunAsyncTask(function() Print("Hello, world!\n"); end);;
Hello, world!
]]></Example>

Such a task cannot be waited for and its result (if any) is ignored.
<P/>
Task arguments are generally copied so that both the task that created them and the task that uses them can access the
data concurrently without fear of race conditions. To avoid copying, arguments should be made shared or public (see the
relevant parts of the section on ); shared and public arguments will not be copied.
<P/>
HPC-GAP currently has multiple implementations of the task API. To enable the reference implementation, set the
environment variable <C>GAP_STDTASKS</C> to a non-empty value before starting GAP.
  </Section>

  <Section Label="Running tasks">
    <Heading>Running tasks</Heading>
    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="RunTask" Arg='func [, arg1, ..., argn]'/>
      <Description>
        <Ref Func='RunTask'/> prepares a task for execution and starts it. The task will call the function <A>func</A> with arguments
        <A>arg1</A> through <A>argn</A> (if provided). The return value of <A>func</A> is the result of the task.

        The <Ref Func='RunTask'/> call itself returns a task object that can be used by functions that expect a task argument.
      </Description>
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="ScheduleTask" Arg='condition, func [, arg1, ...,argn]'/>
      <Description>
        <Ref Func='ScheduleTask'/> prepares a task for execution, but, unlike <Ref Func='RunTask'/> does not start it until <A>condition</A>
        is met. See  on how to construct conditions. Simple examples of conditions are individual tasks, where execution occurs after
        the task completes, or lists of tasks, where execution occurs after all tasks in the list complete.

        <Example><![CDATA[
gap> t1 := RunTask(x->x*x, 3);;
gap> t2 := RunTask(x->x*x, 4);;
gap> t := ScheduleTask([t1, t2], function()
>           return TaskResult(t1) + TaskResult(t2);
>    end);
gap> TaskResult(t);
25
]]></Example>
        While the above example could also be achieved with <Ref Func='RunTask'/> in lieu of <Ref Func='ScheduleTask'/>, since
        <Ref Func='TaskResult'/> would wait for <A>t1</A> and <A>t2</A> to complete, the above implementation does not actually start
        the final task until the others are complete, making it more efficient, since no additional worker thread needs to be
        occupied.

      </Description>  
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="DelayTask" Arg='func [, arg1, ..., argn]'/>
      <Description>
      <Ref Func="DelayTask"/> works as <Ref Func="RunTask"/>, but its start is delayed until it is being waited for (including
      implicitly by calling <Ref Func="TaskResult"/>).
      </Description>
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="RunAsyncTask" Arg='func [, arg1, ..., argn]'/>
      <Description>
        <Ref Func="RunAsyncTask"/> creates an asynchronous task. It works like <Ref Func="RunTask"/>, except that its result will be
        ignored.
      </Description> 
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="ScheduleAsyncTask" Arg='condition, func, [, arg1, ..., argn]'/>
      <Description>
        <Ref Func="ScheduleAsyncTask"/> creates an asynchronous task. It works like <Ref Func="ScheduleTask"/>,
        except that its result will be ignored.
      </Description>
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="MakeTaskAsync" Arg='task'/>
      <Description>
        <Ref Func="MakeTaskAsync"/> turns a synchronous task into an asynchronous task that cannot be waited for and whose result will
        be ignored.
      </Description>
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="ImmediateTask" Arg='func [, arg1, ..., argn]'/>
      <Description>
        <Ref Func="ImmediateTask"/> executes the task specified by its arguments synchronously, usually within the current thread.
      </Description>
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="ExecuteTask" Arg='task'/>
      <Description>
        <Ref Func="ExecuteTask"/> starts <A>task</A> if it is not already running. It has only an effect if its argument is a task
        returned by <Ref Func="DelayTask"/>; otherwise, it is a no-op.
      </Description>
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="WaitTask" Arg='task1,...,taskn'/>
      <Func Name="WaitTask" Arg='condition' Label="with a condition" />
      <Func Name="WaitTasks" Arg='task1,...,taskn'/>

      <Description>
        <Ref Func="WaitTask"/> waits until <A>task1</A> through <A>taskn</A> have completed; after that, it returns.

        Alternatively, a condition can be passed to <Ref Func="WaitTask"/> in order to wait until a condition is met. See  on how to
        construct conditions.

        <Ref Func="WaitTasks"/> is an alias for <Ref Func="WaitTask"/>.
      </Description>
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="WaitAnyTask" Arg='task1, ..., taskn'/>
      <Description>
        The <Ref Func="WaitAnyTask"/> function waits for any of its arguments to finish, then returns the number of that task.

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> task1 := DelayTask(x->SortedList(x), [3,2,1]);;
gap> task2 := DelayTask(x->SortedList(x), [6,5,4]);;
gap> which := WaitAnyTask(task1, task2);
2
gap> if which = 1 then
>      Display(TaskResult(task1));Display(TaskResult(task2));
>    else
>      Display(TaskResult(task2));Display(TaskResult(task1));
>    fi;
[ 4, 5, 6 ]
[ 1, 2, 3 ]
]]></Example>

One can pass a list of tasks to <C>WaitAnyTask</C> as an argument; <C>WaitAnyTask([task1, ..., taskn])</C> behaves
identically to <C>WaitAnyTask(task1, ..., taskn)</C>.

      </Description>
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="TaskResult" Arg='task'/>
      <Description>
        The <Ref Func="TaskResult"/> function returns the result of a task. It implicitly calls <Ref Func="WaitTask"/> if that is
        necessary. Multiple invocations of <Ref Func="TaskResult"/> with the same task argument will not do repeated waits and always
        return the same value.
      </Description>
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="CurrentTask" Arg=''/>
      <Description>
        The <Ref Func="CurrentTask"/> returns the currently running task.
      </Description>
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="RunningTasks" Arg=''/>
      <Description>
        This function returns the number of currently running tasks. Note that it is only an approximation and can change as new
        tasks are being started by other threads.
      </Description>
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="TaskStarted" Arg='task'/>
      <Description>
        This function returns true if the task has started executing (i.e., for any non-delayed task), false otherwise.
      </Description>
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="TaskFinished" Arg='task'/>
      <Description>
        This function returns true if the task has finished executing and its result is available, false otherwise.
      </Description>
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="TaskIsAsync" Arg='task'/>
      <Description>
        This function returns true if the task is asynchronous, true otherwise.
      </Description>
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="CullIdleTasks" Arg=''/>
      <Description>
        This function terminates unused worker threads.
      </Description>
    </ManSection>
  </Section>

  <Section Label="Cancelling tasks">
    <Heading>Cancelling tasks</Heading>
    HPC-GAP uses a cooperative model for task cancellation. A programmer can request the cancellation of another task, but
    it is up to that other task to actually terminate itself. The tasks library has functions to request cancellation, to
    test for the cancellation state of a task, and to perform actions in response to cancellation requests.

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="CancelTask" Arg='task'/>
      <Description>
        <Ref Func="CancelTask"/> submits a request that <A>task</A> is to be cancelled.
      </Description>
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="TaskCancellationRequested" Arg='task'/>
      <Description>
        <Ref Func="TaskCancellationRequested"/> returns true if <Ref Func="CancelTask"/> has been called for <A>task</A>,
        false otherwise.
      </Description>
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="OnTaskCancellation" Arg='exit_func'/>
      <Description>
        <Ref Func="OnTaskCancellation"/> tests if cancellation for the current task has been requested. If so,
        then <A>exit_func</A> will be called (as a parameterless function) and the current task will be aborted.
        The result of the current task will be the value of <A>exit_func()</A>.

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> task := RunTask(function()
>      while true do
>        OnTaskCancellation(function() return 314; end);
>      od;
>    end);
gap> CancelTask(task);
gap> TaskResult(task);
314
]]></Example>
      </Description>
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="OnTaskCancellationReturn" Arg='value'/>
      <Description>
        <Ref Func="OnTaskCancellationReturn"/> is a convenience function that does the same as:
<Example><![CDATA[
OnTaskCancellation(function() return value; end);
]]></Example>
      </Description>
    </ManSection>

  </Section>

  <Section Label="Conditions">
    <Heading>Conditions</Heading>

    <Ref Func="ScheduleTask"/> and <Ref Func="WaitTask"/> can be made to wait on more complex conditions than just tasks.
    A condition is either a milestone, a task, or a list of milestones and tasks. <Ref Func="ScheduleTask"/> starts its
    task and <Ref Func="WaitTask"/> returns when the condition has been met.
    A condition represented by a task is met when the task has completed. A
    condition represented by a milestone is met when the milestone has been achieved (see below). A condition represented by
    a list is met when all conditions in the list have been met.
  </Section>

  <Section Label="Milestones">
    <Heading>Milestones</Heading>

    Milestones are a way to represent abstract conditions to which multiple tasks can contribute.

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="NewMilestone" Arg='[list]'/>
      <Description>
        The <Ref Func="NewMilestone"/> function creates a new milestone. Its argument is a list of targets,
        which must be a list of integers and/or strings. If omitted, the list defaults to <C>[0]</C>.
      </Description>
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="ContributeToMilestone" Arg='milestone, target'/>
      <Description>
        The <Ref Func="ContributeToMilestone"/> milestone function contributes the specified target to the
        milestone. Once all targets have been contributed to a milestone, it has been achieved.
      </Description>
    </ManSection>

    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="AchieveMilestone" Arg='milestone'/>
      <Description>
        The <Ref Func="AchieveMilestone"/> function allows a program to achieve a milestone in a single step
        without adding individual targets to it. This is most useful in conjunction with the default value for
        <Ref Func="NewMilestone"/>, e.g.
<Example><![CDATA[
gap> m := NewMilestone();;
gap> AchieveMilestone(m);
]]></Example>
      </Description>
    </ManSection>>
    
    <ManSection>
      <Func Name="IsMilestoneAchieved" Arg='milestone'/>
      <Description>
        <Ref Func="IsMilestoneAchieved"/> tests explicitly if a milestone has been achieved. It returns
        <C>true</C> on success, <C>false</C> otherwise.
<Example><![CDATA[
gap> m := NewMilestone([1,2]);;
gap> ContributeToMilestone(m, 1);
gap> IsMilestoneAchieved(m);
false
gap> ContributeToMilestone(m, 2);
gap> IsMilestoneAchieved(m);
true
]]></Example>
      </Description>
    </ManSection>
  </Section>
</Chapter>
