<?xml version="2.1" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE Book SYSTEM "gapdoc.dtd">

<Book Name="tomlib">                                        <!-- REQUIRED -->
	
	<!--
	    The title page
	    -->
	<TitlePage>    
		<!-- REQUIRED -->
		<Title>                                             
			<Package>The GAP Table Of Marks Package</Package>
		</Title>
		
		<Subtitle>     	                                     <!-- OPTIONAL -->
			<Br/>
			
			&nbsp;
		</Subtitle>
		
		<Version>Version</Version> 
		<!-- OPTIONAL -->
		<Author> 
			Liam Naughton<Br/>                 <!-- REQUIRED -->
			&nbsp;
			<Address>
				Department of Mathematics,<Br/>
				National University of Ireland Galway,<Br/>
				Galway,<Br/>
				Ireland.
			</Address>
			<Email> liam.naughton@nuigalway.ie</Email> 
			<Homepage>http://schmidt.nuigalway.ie/tomlib</Homepage>
		</Author> 
		
		<Date>March 2009</Date> 
		<!-- OPTIONAL -->
		
		<Copyright> 
			<!-- OPTIONAL -->
			&copyright; 2009 Liam Naughton.
		</Copyright> 
		
		<Acknowledgements> 
			<!-- OPTIONAL -->
			<P/>
			
			<Package></Package>.
			
			<P/>This documentation was prepared with the <Package>GAPDoc</Package> package 
			by Frank Luebeck and Max Neunhoffer. 
		</Acknowledgements>
		
	</TitlePage>
	
	
	
	<TableOfContents/>                                    <!-- OPTIONAL -->
	
	
	
	<!--
	    The document
	    -->
	<Body>                                                <!-- REQUIRED -->
		
		
  <Chapter>
	  <Heading>The GAP Table of Marks Package</Heading>
	  
	  
	  <Section><Heading>Tables Of Marks</Heading>
		  
		  The concept of a <E>Table of Marks</E> was introduced by W.Burnside in his
		  book ``Theory of Groups of Finite  Order''. Therefore a table of marks is sometimes called a <E>Burnside matrix</E>.
		  
		  The table of marks of a finite group <M>G</M>  is a matrix whose rows and
		  columns are labelled by the conjugacy classes of subgroups of <M>G</M>
		  and where for two subgroups <M>H</M> and <M>K</M> the <M>(H, K)</M>--entry is
		  the number of fixed points of <M>K</M> in the transitive action of <M>G</M>
		  on the cosets of <M>H</M> in <M>G</M>.
		  So the table of marks characterizes the set of all permutation
		  representations of <M>G</M>.
		  
		  Moreover, the table of marks gives a compact description of the subgroup
		  lattice of <M>G</M>, since from the numbers of fixed points the numbers of
		  conjugates of a subgroup <M>K</M> contained in a subgroup <M>H</M> can be derived.
		  
		  For small groups the table of marks of <M>G</M> can be constructed directly in GAP by first computing the entire subgroup lattice of <M>G</M>. However, for larger groups this method is unfeasible. The GAP Table of Marks package provides access to several hundred table of marks and their maximal subgroups. 
		 
		  
		
		  
	  </Section>

	  <Section>
		  <Heading>Installing The Table of Marks Package</Heading>
		  
		  Download the archives in your preferred format. Unpack the archives inside the pkg dirctory of your GAP installation.
		 Load the package
		<Log>
gap&gt; LoadPackage("tomlib");
true
		</Log>
	  </Section>
	  <Section>
		  <Heading>Contents of the Tomlib Package</Heading>
		  For a complete list of the contents of the tomlib package do the following.
<Log>
gap&gt; names:=AllLibTomNames();;
gap&gt; "A5" in names;
true
</Log>
The current version of the tomlib package contains tables of marks of the groups listed below as well as of selected maximal subgroups.
<List>
</List>

The Alternating groups <M>A_n</M>
<List>
<Item>  for <M> n = 6,7,8,9,10,11 </M>.</Item>
</List>
The Symmetric groups <M>S_n</M>
<List>
<Item>  for <M>n = 6,7,8,9,10,11,12 </M>.</Item>
</List>
The Janko groups
<List>
<Item> <M>J_1, J_2, J_3</M>.</Item>
</List>
The Mathieu groups
<List>
<Item> <M>M_{11}, M_{12}, M_{22}, M_{23}, M_{24}</M>.</Item>
</List>
The Linear Groups 
<M>L_{2}(n)</M> for
<List>
<Item> <M>n = 7, 8, 11, 13, 16, 17, 19, 23, 25, 27, 29, 31, 32, 37, 41, 43, 47, 49, 53</M></Item>
<Item> <M>n =  59, 61, 64, 67, 71, 73, 79, 81, 83, 89, 97, 101, 103, 107, 109, 113, 121, 125 .</M></Item>
</List>
along with
<List>
<Item><M>L_{3}(4), L_{3}(3),L_{3}(5), L_{3}(7), L_{3}(9)</M></Item>
<Item><M>L_{4}(3), L_{3}(8), L_{3}(11) </M>.</Item>
</List>


The Unitary Groups 
<List>
<Item><M>U_{3}(3), U_{4}(3), U_{3}(5), U_{3}(4), U_{3}(11), U_{3}(7), U_{3}(8)</M></Item>
<Item><M>U_{3}(9), U_{4}(2), U_{5}(2)</M></Item>
</List>
The Higman-Sims group
<List>
<Item> <M>HS</M></Item>
</List>
The McLaughlin groups
<List>
<Item> <M>Mc L</M></Item>
</List>
The Held group
<List>
<Item> <M>He</M></Item>
</List>
The names given to each subgroup are consistent with those used in Robert Wilon's atlas http://for.mat.bham.ac.uk/atlas/v2.0/.
For example if you wish to acces the table of marks of the maximal subgroup <M>"5:4\times A5"</M> of the Higman-Sims group do the following:
<Log>
gap&gt; TableOfMarks("5:4XA5");
TableOfMarks( "5:4xA5" )
</Log>
</Section>

<Section>
<Heading>Whats new in this version of tomlib</Heading>
The changes with respect to previous versions of tomlib are listed below



This list contains the changes in the GAP Library of Tables of Marks since the release of TomLib 1.0 (together with GAP 4.3) in May 2002. We denote mathematical errors by *** and new information by NEW. We use C to denote changes that are not obviously corrections; the number of these changes is kept small.


Release of TomLib 1.1.1 (December 2003)


Changes are assigned to the simple group involved, and shown in alphabetical order.
<List>
<Item>***	   <M>3D_{4}(2)</M>	     		
The derived subgroups for the classes 2847 and 2848 were corrected, they are in the classes 2823 and 2827, respectively (not 2847 and 2848) .
</Item>
<Item>***	   	      		
	The derived subgroups for the last classes in the maximal subgroups <M>S_{3} \times L_{2}(8)</M> and <M>(7 \times L_{2}(7)):3</M> were corrected, they are in the last but one class not in the last .
</Item>
<Item>***	   <M>Co3</M>	      		
The derived subgroups for the classes 2018, 2318, and 2457 in <M>Co3</M> were corrected, they are in the classes 1435, 2048, and 2442, respectively (not 2018, 2318, and 2457) .
</Item>
<Item>***	   	      		
	The derived subgroups for the last classes in the maximal subgroups <M>2 \times M_{12}, S_{3} \times L_{2}(8):3</M>, and <M>A_{4} \times S_{5}</M> were corrected, they are in the classes 514, 139, and 138, respectively (not 515, 144, and 146) .
</Item>
<Item>***	   <M>L_{3}(4)</M>	     		
The derived subgroups for the class 199 in <M>3.L_{3}(4).23</M> were corrected, they are in the class 198 not 199 .
</Item>
<Item>***	   	     		
The generators for the representative of the class 706 in <M>22.L_{3}(4).22</M> were replaced; the former generators belonged to a group in class 705 .
</Item>
<Item>***	   <M>O_{8}^{-}(2)</M>	      		
The straight line programs were corrected; up to now, the corresponding data stored in the table did not describe valid straight line programs .
</Item>
<Item>***	   	     		
	The derived subgroups for the last class in the maximal subgroup <M>(S_{3} \times S_{3} \times A_{5}):2</M> of <M>O_{8}^{-}(2)</M> were corrected, they are in the class 362 not 368 .
</Item>
<Item>***	   <M>U_{3}(4)</M>	     		
The derived subgroups for the class 80 in <M>U+{3}(4).2</M> were corrected, they are in the class 79 not 80 .
</Item>
<Item>***	   <M>U_{4}(2)</M>	     		
	The generators for the representative of the class 110 in the maximal subgroup <M>2.(A_{4} \times A_{4}).2.2</M> of <M>U_{4}(2).2</M> were replaced; the former generators belonged to a group of order 24 not 12, which was conjugate to the representative of class 152 .
</Item>
<Item>***	   <M>U_{4}(3)</M>	  		
The generators for the representatives of the classes 575 and 595 in <M>U_{4}(3).21</M> were replaced; the former generators belonged to groups of order 192 not 96, which were conjugate to the representative of class 709 .
</Item>
</List>


Release of TomLib 1.1.2 (February 2004)


Changes are assigned to the simple group involved, and shown in alphabetical order.
<List>
<Item>***	   <M>O_{8}^{-}(2)</M>	  		
The derived subgroups for the class 5269 were corrected, they are in the class 5108 not 5269 .
</Item>
<Item>***	   		
	The fusion from the table of marks of the maximal subgroup <M>(A_{8} \times 3):2</M> was corrected .
</Item>
</List>

Release of TomLib 1.1.3 (September 2007)


Changes are assigned to the simple group involved, and shown in alphabetical order.
<List>
<Item>NEW	   <M>A_{12}</M>	   
The table of marks of <M>S_{12}</M> was added .
</Item>
<Item>NEW	   <M>A_{13}</M>	     		
The table of marks of <M>A_{13}</M> was added .
</Item>
</List>

Release of TomLib 1.1.4 (November 2008)


Changes are assigned to the simple group involved, and shown in alphabetical order.
<List>
<Item>
<M>A_{12}</M> The underlying group of the table of marks of <M>S_{12}</M> was in fact <M>S_{13}</M>, acting on 13 points. Moreover, it had the group order of <M>S_{12}</M> stored.
</Item>
</List>

</Section>
 </Chapter>
 
  
  
</Body>


<TheIndex/>  
</Book>



	  