<Chapter Label="ChangesGAP47toGAP48"> 
<Heading>Changes between &GAP; 4.7 and &GAP; 4.8</Heading>

This chapter contains an overview of most important changes 
introduced in &GAP; 4.8.0 release (the beta release of &GAP; 4.8).
Later it will also contain information about subsequent update 
releases for &GAP; 4.8.

First of all, &GAP; development repository is now hosted on GitHub at
<URL>https://github.com/gap-system/gap</URL>, and &GAP; 4.8 is the first 
major &GAP; release made from this repository. The public issue tracker
for the core &GAP; system is located at 
<URL>https://github.com/gap-system/gap/issues</URL>,
and you may use appropriate milestones from 
<URL>https://github.com/gap-system/gap/milestones</URL> to see all changes
that were introduced in corresponding &GAP; releases. An overview of the
most significant ones is provided below.

<Section Label="gap480"> 
<Heading>&GAP; 4.8.0 (Autumn 2015)</Heading>

<Subsection Label="Changes in the core GAP48 system"> 
<Heading>Changes in the core &GAP; system introduced in &GAP; 4.8</Heading>

Improved and extended functionality:
<List>
<Item>
Unnecessary tests for the finiteness of the field were removed from 
<Ref Func="GModuleByMats" BookName="ref"/> and related functions 
(those that do not need MeatAxe, but just linear algebra).
Thus the correponding functions will work in the case of characteristic 0
or for other infinite fields, too.
</Item> 
<!-- https://github.com/gap-system/gap/pull/192 -->
<Item>Extended support for accessing lists using multiple indices and
indexing into lists using indices other than positive small integers.
This allows library or packages to install methods supporting expressions 
like
<Log><![CDATA[
m[1,2];
m[1,2,3] := x;
IsBound(m["a","b",Z(7)]);
Unbind(m[1][2,3])
]]></Log>
</Item>
<Item>
The most common cases of <Ref Oper="AddDictionary" BookName="ref"/> 
on three arguments now bypass method selection, avoiding the cost 
of determining homogeneity for plain lists of mutable objects.
</Item>
<Item> 
<!-- https://github.com/gap-system/gap/issues/7 -->
Package authors may optionally specify the source code repository,
issue tracker and support email address for their package using new
components in the <File>PackageInfo.g</File> file, which will be used
to create hyperlinks from the package overview page (see 
<File>PackageInfo.g</File> from the Example package which you may use
as a template).
</Item>
</List>

Changed functionality:
<List>  
<Item>
<!-- https://github.com/gap-system/gap/pull/90 -->
Added support for partially variadic functions to allow function expressions
like
<Log><![CDATA[
function(a,b,c,arg) ... end;
]]></Log>
which would require at least three arguments and assign the first three 
to <A>a</A>, <A>b</A> and <A>c</A> and then a list containing any remaining 
ones to <A>arg</A>.
<P/>
This may break an existing code when <A>arg</A> is used as a name of the
argument which is not the last one.
</Item>
<Item>
As a preparation for the future migration to the multithreaded &GAP;&nbsp;5,
some language extensions from the <Package>HPC-GAP</Package> project were
backported to the &GAP; library to help to unify the codebase of both 
&GAP;&nbsp;4 and &GAP;&nbsp;5. At the moment, the only change which is not
backwards compatible is <C>atomic</C> is no longer a valid identifier in 
&GAP;&nbsp;4 since it is reserved as a keyword for  &GAP;&nbsp;5.
</Item>
</List>

Fixed bugs:

<List>
<Item>
A combination of two bugs could lead to a segfault. First off,
<Ref Func="NullMat" BookName="ref"/> (and various other &GAP; functions),
when asked to produce matrix over a small field, called 
<Ref Func="ConvertToMatrixRep" BookName="ref"/>. After this, if the user
tried to changed one of the entries to a value from a larger extension
field, this resulted in an error. (This is now fixed).
<P/>
Unfortunately, the C code catching this error had a bug and allowed
users to type <Q>return</Q> to continue while ignoring the conversion
error. This was a bad idea, as the C code would be in an inconsistent
state at this point, subsequently leading to a crash.
<P/>
This, too, has been fixed, by not allowing the user to ignore the error
by entering <Q>return</Q>.
</Item>
<Item>
<!-- https://github.com/gap-system/gap/pull/243/ -->
<Ref Oper="PowerMod" BookName="ref"/> produced wrong results for univariate 
Laurent polynomials when the two polynomial arguments are stored with the 
same non-zero shift.
</Item>
</List>

</Subsection>

<Subsection Label="New and updated packages since GAP 4.7.8"> 
<Heading>New and updated packages since &GAP; 4.7.8</Heading>

<Index>Packages, new</Index>
At the time of the release of &GAP; 4.7.8 there were 119 packages 
redistributed with &GAP;. New packages that have been added to the 
redistribution since the release of &GAP; 4.7.8 are: 

<List>
<Item>
<Package>matgrp</Package> package by Alexander Hulpke, which provides
an interface to the solvable radical functionality for matrix groups,
building on constructive recognition.
</Item>
</List>

</Subsection>

</Section>

</Chapter>


<!-- %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% --> 
<!-- %% --> 
<!-- %E -->
